REPORTER: This is Phil Malone for the County Show
Hier ist Phil Malone für die County Show
at the Victoria Centre in Palk Road in Wellingborough.
im Park Road Victoria Centre in Wellingborough.
With me is Mataji, who teaches Sahaja Yoga.
Bei mir ist Shri Mataji, die Sahaja Yoga unterrichtet.
Now, Mataji, what exactly does this yoga involve?
Mataji, was genau ist dieses Yoga?
SHRI MATAJI: Sahaja means: “saha” means with, “ja” is born.
“Saha” bedeutet "mit" und “ja” - "geboren".
So whatever is born with you means spontaneous.
Es ist also angeboren und spontan.
It is a living process of the living force, which is surrounding us,
Es ist lebendig, eine lebendige Kraft, die uns umgibt,
which is everywhere, which pulsates in everything.
die überall ist und in allem pulsiert.
And this happening is the breakthrough,
Und was damit geschieht, ist ein Durchbruch,
the ultimate breakthrough into our unconscious;
der endgültige Durchbruch zu unserem Unbewussten,
can be described psychologically.
um es psychologisch zu beschreiben.
REPORTER: So some people call this self-realization.
Manche nennen das die Selbstverwirklichung.
SHRI MATAJI: Same.
Das ist das Gleiche.
REPORTER: Now, Your background is from a Christian family in India.
Sie kommen ja aus einer christlichen Familie in Indien.
Yes.
Ja.
REPORTER: Is Your teaching involved with Christianity or not?
Hat Ihre Lehre etwas mit dem Christentum zu tun oder nicht?
SHRI MATAJI: It is, of course,
Natürlich,
because Christ is very important for Sahaja Yoga, no doubt.
denn Christus ist sehr wichtig für Sahaja Yoga, das ist ganz klar.
But the way we understand Christ
Aber das Bild von Christus
out of the text of Bible is very limited.
in den Bibeltexten ist sehr begrenzt.
We have to see to other texts about Him, and expand,
Aber wir sollten auch sehen, was andere Texte über Ihn sagen,
and explain Him, what He meant,
wie sie Seine Bedeutung erklären,
because Bible is not sufficient to explain Him.
denn die Erklärungen der Bibel sind nicht ausreichend.
REPORTER: So, is Your message one of peace and that’s, in that case,
Ist Ihre Botschaft denn eine des Friedens,
peace in the rest of the world or peace within people?
Frieden in der Welt und Frieden in den Menschen?
SHRI MATAJI: Absolutely.
Absolut!
Peace within will only bring the peace outside.
Nur innerer Frieden wird auch äußeren Frieden bringen.
Whatever we are inside is expressed outside.
Alles, was wir in uns tragen, spiegelt sich im Außen.
REPORTER: Now, You have had some successes
Sie haben auch einige Male erfolgreich
in curing people or healing people in the past.
Menschen geheilt in der Vergangenheit.
Is this because You work from the inside out or how do You do it?
Ist das möglich, weil Sie umgekehrt arbeiten, von innen nach außen?
SHRI MATAJI: It’s just very simple because
Es ist ganz einfach,
you have the vitality, that Force is vitality itself.
Sie haben die Lebenskraft. Diese Kraft ist die Lebenskraft selbst.
And once you have that flowing through you,
Uns wenn Sie in Ihnen fließt,
if you give that vitality to someone, that person is revitalized.
und Sie jemandem diese Kraft geben, wird derjenige neu belebt.
In simple words you can say like that.
So kann man es in einfachen Worten ausdrücken.
But actually it is a happening within you which takes place.
Aber eigentlich findet etwas in Ihnen statt.
There is a residual force, the germinating force you can call it,
Es gibt eine Restkraft, die Keimkraft könnte man sagen,
or the ascending force within you,
oder eine aufsteigende Kraft in Ihnen,
which rises and gives you the experience of your Spirit.
die emporsteigt, so dass Sie Ihren Spirit wahrnehmen.
Means your Spirit comes into your attention,
Das heißt, Ihr Spirit kommt in Ihre Aufmerksamkeit.
means you can feel it on your central nervous system.
Und Sie können ihn auf Ihrem zentralen Nervensystem spüren.
So you receive the information
Sie bekommen also die Information,
or, we can say, you become enlightened by the Spirit,
oder anders gesagt: Sie werden erleuchtet durch Ihren Spirit,
which is the Absolute.
der das Absolute ist.
Once you receive the Absolute, as a by-product of that
Sobald dieses Absolute in Ihnen erweckt ist, werden als Nebeneffekt
all these things drop out, all your maladjustments and everything.
alle schlechten Angewohnheiten und all diese Dinge von Ihnen gehen.
REPORTER: Now, tonight You’re appearing in Northampton
Heute Abend werden Sie in Northhampton sprechen,
at the Guildhall.  SHRI MATAJI: Yes.
in der Guildhall. Ja.
REPORTER: If people went along,
Wenn Leute dorthin gehen,
what would You have to say to them tonight?
was werden Sie Ihnen heute Abend sagen?
SHRI MATAJI: I’ll have to explain to them what actually they are.
Ich muss ihnen erklären, was sie in Wirklichkeit sind.
Actually they are the Spirit,
In Wirklichkeit sind sie der Spirit,
and this body, mind
und dieser Körper, dieser Verstand,
and all these things are just the covering.
all diese Dinge verdecken das nur.
Now our attention is at our body level,
Jetzt ist unsere Aufmerksamkeit auf der Ebene unserer Körper,
at the level of our mind, or emotions.
unseres Verstands und unserer Gefühle.
But you have to go beyond, and with this happening it happens.
Aber wir müssen darüber hinaus gehen, und das wird geschehen.
When it happens, you become the twice-born, as they call it,
Wenn es geschieht, werden Sie ein "Zweimal-Geborener", wie es heißt,
like an egg becoming a bird the transformation takes place.
so wie ein Ei zum Vogel wird, so eine Transformation ist das.
REPORTER: So this second birth coming, some people
Von dieser zweiten Geburt denken manche doch,
perhaps they believe this would happen when they die.
dass dies vielleicht nach dem Tod geschieht.
SHRI MATAJI: It’s not possible. How can that be?
Das ist unmöglich. Wie könnte das sein?
That’s a misunderstanding. There are lots of misunderstandings
Das ist ein falsches Verständnis. Über diese Dinge
we have about these things, which can be removed.
gibt es viele Missverständnisse, die beseitigt werden können.
First logically we have to reach certain conclusions, logically.
Zuerst müssen wir ganz logisch bestimmte Schlussfolgerungen ziehen.
So that we don’t put our brain a complete stop,
Wir hören nicht völlig auf, unser Gehirn zu benutzen.
we see through our logical understanding
Mit unserer Logik können wir verstehen,
that what we have to achieve, if it’s a living force.
dass das, was wir erreichen müssen, wenn es eine lebendige Kraft ist,
Then we achieve it.
auch erreicht wird.
Once we achieve it, then we have to verify it
Wenn wir diesen Punkt erreichen, dann müssen wir überprüfen,
if it is so or not. It’s all absolutely open.
ob es wirklich so ist. Alles ist völlig offen.
REPORTER: So, are Your followers then…
Ihre Anhänger,
how do they practice this form of yoga?
wie praktizieren Sie diese Form des Yogas?
I mean, do they do it in conjunction with other religions, for example?
Tun sie es zum Beispiel in Verbindung mit anderen Religionen?
SHRI MATAJI: You see, these religions that you see,
Die Religionen, die Sie sehen,
outside they look like different religions
sehen äußerlich wie unterschiedliche Religionen aus,
but actually they are one.
aber im Grunde sind sie eins.
All these are flowers out of one tree of life.
Sie alle sind Blumen des einen Baums des Lebens.
They are different flowers to look at, but they are not.
Sie sehen unterschiedlich aus, aber sie sind es nicht.
They are living on the same truth,
Sie stehen auf der gleichen Wahrheit,
there’s no difference at all between them.
es gibt keinen Unterschied zwischen ihnen.
But when you pluck them and call them “this is mine, this is mine,”
Aber wenn sie gepflückt werden und geschrien wird: "Die gehört mir",
they become dead, ugly, and funny.
sterben sie ab, sie werden hässlich und seltsam.
That’s how fanaticism has come. All religions are born out of truth
So entstand Fanatismus. Alle Religionen basieren auf Wahrheit,
and here you find the integration of them, complete integration.
und in Sahaja Yoga werden sie alle vereint, vollständig eins.
REPORTER: Well, You’ll be meeting with people from Northampton
Heute Abend werden Sie Menschen aus Northhampton
and from the rest of the county in the Guildhall tonight
und der ganzen Region in der Guildhall treffen.
and thank You very much for speaking with us.
Vielen Dank für das Gespräch.
SHRI MATAJI: The address is:
Die Adresse ist:
Guildhall, St. Giles’ Square, Northampton.
Guildhall, St. Giles’ Square, Northampton.
REPORTER: And it starts at about half past seven.
Und Beginn ist um 19.30 Uhr.
SHRI MATAJI: Yes, half past seven it will start. I hope to see-
Ja, es beginnt um halb 8. Ich hoffe, viele zu sehen.
REPORTER: Thank You very much. This is Phil Malone for the County Show
Dankeschön. Das war Phil Malone für die County Show
at the Victoria Centre, Palk Road, in Wellingborough.
im Victoria Centre in Wellingborough.
SHRI MATAJI: Was that good? REPORTER: That’s great, that’s fine, yes, thanks very much.
War das gut? Ja, wunderbar. Vielen Dank!
...take these flowers with You, all right.
Nehmen Sie bitte diese Blumen.
SHRI MATAJI: You should have asked about gurus,
Sie hätten nach Gurus fragen sollen,
I think that’s important. REPORTER: [unclear].
das halte Ich für wichtig.
SHRI MATAJI: That’s very important, you know,
Es ist sehr wichtig,
because all the people are misled by gurus
weil all die Leute von Gurus irregeführt werden,
and all this hypnotic stuff, and black magic.
und all diese Hypnoseangebote und schwarze Magie.
You must save all these people. That’s very important.
Davor müssen Sie diese Leute bewahren. Das ist sehr wichtig.
R: Yes, they get confused, do they?
Ja, sie kommen durcheinander, oder?
SHRI MATAJI: Very much confused, you see, the confusion is so much.
Ja sehr. Sie sind sehr verwirrt.
That’s the sign of modern times also.
Es ist auch typisch für die moderne Zeit.
You must know what to expect. REPORTER: Mm, yes. Anyway all the best,
Sie müssen wissen, was sie erwarten. Mm, ja. Dann alles Gute.
Thanks very much indeed.
Vielen Dank.
REPORTER: Thank You, OK, [unclear]. SHRI MATAJI: Thank you very much.
Danke!
REPORTER: OK, Thank You, [UNCLEAR]. SHRI MATAJI: Sorry I was late,
Entschuldigung, dass Ich zu spät kam,
but yesterday was such a funny experience.
aber gestern ist etwas sehr Komisches passiert.
We came down
Wir kamen und waren
running out forty miles, and nothing happened.
nach fast 60 km Fahrt, und nichts passierte.
Thank you very much, thank you. Good-bye.
Vielen Dank. Auf Wiedersehen.